Oh my goodness. I warned you that this
was going to be all me talking for for
today, but thank you for bearing with
me. We're we're most of the way through.
And I know for some of you this is this
is all old news as I say, but hopefully
there's some interesting things there.
Maybe you disagree with me on some
points. In which case, please do put it
in the Q&A. Nothing I like more than
than good debate. Agents.md I've
mentioned it several times. This of
course is the file which you use to give
to to to prep your LLM with some
information. It's particularly it's used
by coding agents and it's a markdown
file. MD is is short for markdown which
is a sort of shorthand form. It was it
sort of inspired by by thinking of a way
that we could have something that could
represent an HTML page, a web page with
with a sort of simpler, more more human
readable and writable uh version of it
rather than all of the tags you see in
HTML. So so uh the the the simple idea
of this if you're not familiar with
markdown is that if you see like like
like a hash a single hash like it says
there with hash project summary that
means a a big heading an H1. Two hashes
is like an H2. Three hashes is like an
H3. So, it lets you have a sort of
hierarchy of headings. And otherwise,
it's pretty simple. Numbered lists,
hyphens for bulleted lists, that kind of
stuff. You pick it up fast. It's like a
text file with some some useful extra
characters to show like a like a markup
styling. And this is a format which LLMs
love. They love markdown because they've
been trained with lots and lots of
markdown. They've generated lots of
markdown. They just love making markdown
files and they love reading them and
they're easy to write as well. So, it
makes absolute sense that we would use
these kinds of markdown files to prep
our agents. and you write them in
natural language style, just like you
might write a prompt to an LLM, which
means you want it to be nice and concise
and crisp and assertive and not have too
much ambiguity and and really u have as
much signal as you can in in the words
that you use. That's some of the tricks.
This, of course, gets squashed into your
context window. So, this is precious
space. So, you don't want to be verbose.
You want to make every word count. And
so, as I say, it's a markdown format
file. It gets included in the context
for the agent. And you typically have
one of these files in what's called the
project root directory, which is like
for yesterday, it was the the directory
called instant. It's the directory at
the the top of your project. And that
file will get read in and included in
the context for the LLM. But you can
also have another agents.mmd file in
every subdirectory and at any level of
nesting at a a sub subd directory. And
in that case that agents.mmd file will
only be read in when the agent is
working on files in that sub subd
directory or or any further
subdirectory. So it reads in when when
the agent is working on any file, it
will read in the agents.mmd in that
inner directory and then it will work
backwards through all the parent
directories making sure it's got all of
the relevant agents.md files in context.
And that's why I said that that it's not
true to say that agents.mmd are always
included. They're always included if
it's in the project root, but when it's
in a subdirectory, it's only included if
the agent is working on that that
subfolder. And typically, information
that you put in the most inner
agents.mmd overrides information in any
outer directory. So you can be more
specific. If there's a new rule that
should override the general rule, you
put that deep down in a sub directory.
So that's how this sort of hierarchy of
agents.md files works. And if that's not
clear to you, don't worry because we'll
be doing plenty of it in the next few
weeks. And I say agents.mmd and that is
in fact exactly the name of the file. If
you're using cursor or codeex or github
copilot, claude code uses something
called claude.mmd
and anti-gravity uses something called
gemini.md,
but it's the same idea, a markdown file
that tells the agent what to do that you
could have in the project root or in any
sub directory. And I should mention that
cursor and github copilot have other
kinds of files as well. Like cursor has
these things called rules. Uh but I the
trend that I see is that in time
everyone is converging on these
agents.mmd. So while there are still
people that that use cursor rules uh
that generally speaking more and more
people are just focusing on agents.mmd
that's become the kind of de facto
standard agents.md or or claude.md or
gemini.mmd. Uh that's how people are
doing things these days. But there are
some other approaches too that some of
the tools have specifically for those
tools. So look, we're going to spend a
lot of time looking at what makes a good
agents.mmd and what makes a bad
agents.mmd. And it's best to see that
stuff in practice. But just to give you
a few bit bit of a sense of it, you can
see here the kinds of things that I tend
to try and do in my agents.mmd. I
obviously focus on giving it the overall
project goals um and the success
criteria. I like to give it a a
checklist that it can check things off
on the success criteria so that it's
really forced to go and do that. I also
often list links to other documents that
it can optionally load. We'll we'll
cover that in due course. And then I
like to have the clear coding standards
that apply to this project. And here
it's so important to be concise, to be
specific, uh, and to try and correct for
problems that you've had with the agent
in the past. And of course, this is such
an evolving space, and things that are a
problem for me now may not be a problem
anymore for you. But for example, uh, I
hate the way that these AI agents tend
to over complicate everything. So I
always try and stress simpler is better.
Not too many comments. Comments only
when necessary. Be concise. Have short
read me. I hate the way that LLMs love
generating long wordy readmes. I used to
be used to be so happy when people would
would send me PRs uh uh with with with
code for me to merge into my my open
source repos and they would have all of
these lengthy readmes the first time
this happened a couple of years ago. I
thought, "Wow, that's so kind of that
person to write this long readme." Now I
know better. These LLM generated readmes
are just the worst. Don't do that,
please. So, I always tell the LLM to
make readmes short and no emojis,
please. No emojis. Uh, and then I say
important. It's it it turns out that it
works well to put the word important in
block capitals. Who knew? Important.
Avoid overdefensive programming. Avoid
is instance checks in Python. Just just
horrible hacky stuff. Only manage
exceptions when necessary. They love to
to put tries around everything. And then
for me, because I use UV, the Python
package manager, I might say use uv
always UV run something rather than
Python 3 something. Always, never. Um,
and so you can see some some different
stylistic things there. You probably
know this already, but you use back
ticks to to wrap around code like that.
One back tick if you have some some
inline code, just a little bit of code,
and you do three back ticks if you've
got a whole block of code. three back
ticks code and another three back ticks.
You don't need to remember this because
we'll be doing plenty of it. Just gives
you a sense of how this works. And one
final tip people tend to say for these
things, try and focus on the positives.
Try and focus on things that it should
do. Don't do too many negatives like
like I have there never Python 3. You
can use it from time to time, but not
too many because alans aren't so good at
handling negatives. Strangely, that
they're not so coherent at remembering
things that they are not to do. They are
better at remembering things that they
are to do. So, try and focus on what it
should do. Be concise and try not to
have too much of like do not
overcomplicate that I got in here. But
you don't want too much of that because
they tend to be less coherent with it.
Focus on what it should do, less of what
it should not do. And so a final point
that I'll make here is that there was a
school of thought last year and the
school of thought very much was look
your success with agent coding is from
spending time with a really really
excellent agents.mmd.
That is where you need to sweat. You
need to put time, energy, effort into
agents.mmd. You need to have one at the
top. You need to have one in different
subdirectories. You need to work on
making it really really good and have
other documents that support it. You
need to continually uh supplement with
extra files, extra planning files,
success criteria, steps that need to be
taken to test. You need to continually
rewrite your agents.md again and again,
pruning it, removing things that don't
matter anymore, adding in new things.
And indeed, you can you can have your
LLM rewrite it for you, but giving it
very clear instructions because it is
precious and every every line counts and
and LLMs love to add to agents. MD and
you need to make sure that it's tight
and often stop your AI agent, rewrite,
prune, and then reset and start your
agent again. Fresh context, completely
clear, and new agents.m MD. that it's
it's it's hard work, but that certainly
as of last year was the prevailing way
to get the most value out of AI agents.
And as you can probably tell, there is a
new way, a new school of thought. And
the 2026 mindset, it's a kind of let it
hang out. Be more comfortable giving up
the res. Let it go. you focus on the end
goal. Focus on you what you want the LLM
to achieve at the end of it. Use some of
the new features that we will cover over
the next few weeks, skills, uh having
more loops, using agents, sub agents,
and and having a swarm of different
agents. Let it have the end goal. Let it
self-correct and just let it be. Let it
do its thing. That is the kind of
prevailing 2026 mindset which is quite a
departure from the 2025 mindset. And
again, I hate to break it to you. I hate
to break it to you, but I I am still of
the 2025 school of thought. I think it's
more nuanced than this in a second. I'm
about to take you through uh that that
there are different situations which
lend themselves more to a different kind
of strategy. But personally, I am not
ready to let go of the 2025 approach
yet. Depends on the project, depends on
what you're doing as we will discuss.
But much of the time for me, it's about
the amount of work that I put in to
agents.md and to other parts of
optimizing the context window. It makes
an enormous difference to the output and
I am not yet ready to let it go. Except
except for toy projects like a first
person shooter that we did yesterday. I
let that one go for sure, but for larger
projects, I like to be all over it. And
at least for now, I suggest the same for
you. But it's a changing time. And
increasingly during the course of 2026
and beyond, you should expect to see
people more and more often being willing
just to let it go.